<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nubis PC</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Nubis PC</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 08:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Operations Lead Engineer (OLER)</title>
      <link>/jobs/job1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/jobs/job1/</guid>
      <description>Responsibilities:
 Define and set development, test, release, update, and support processes for the product and service offerings. Implement and set up development, testing, automation tools, and IT infrastructure. Plan the team structure, activities, and participate in project management activities Monitor the processes during the entire lifecycle for its adherence and update or create new processes for improvement. Encourage and build automated processes wherever possible Evaluate / select / build and deploy appropriate CI/CD tools  Requirements:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Runtime Software Engineer (RSER)</title>
      <link>/jobs/job3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/jobs/job3/</guid>
      <description>Responsibilities:
 Develop software for a cutting edge technology project Design and develop reusable and reliable code using at least one of the following: C / Python / GO / C++ / Rust Participate in upstreaming efforts to contribute to open-source projects  Requirements:
 Minimum 3 years of experience in software development BSc or MSc degree in Computer Science/Engineering, Telecommunications or similar Good understanding of best practices in software development Working knowledge of control systems like git Working knowledge of Go Familiarity with container runtimes and orchestrators (Kubernetes) Proficiency in spoken and written English Ability to work in a distributed team  Location:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systems Software Engineer (SSER)</title>
      <link>/jobs/job2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/jobs/job2/</guid>
      <description>Responsibilities:
 Develop software for a cutting edge technology project Design and develop reusable and reliable code using at least one of the following: C / Python / GO / C++ / Rust Participate in upstreaming efforts to contribute to open-source projects  Requirements:
 Minimum 3 years of experience in software development BSc or MSc degree in Computer Science/Engineering, Telecommunications or similar Good understanding of best practices in software development Working knowledge of C Working knowledge of control systems like git Experience with Linux kernel and virtualization development Proficiency in spoken and written English Ability to work in a distributed team  Location:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Office Admin (OAR)</title>
      <link>/jobs/job4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/jobs/job4/</guid>
      <description>Responsibilities:
 Coordinate office activities and operations to secure efficiency and compliance to company policies Supervise administrative staff and divide responsibilities to ensure performance Manage agendas / travel arrangements / appointments etc. Manage phone calls and correspondence (e-mail, letters, packages etc.) Support budgeting and bookkeeping procedures Create and update records and databases with personnel, financial and other data Track stocks of office supplies and place orders when necessary Submit timely reports and prepare presentations/proposals as assigned Assist colleagues whenever necessary  Requirements:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>