<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Completed | Nubificus</title><link>/tag/completed/</link><atom:link href="/tag/completed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Completed</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>/media/logo_hu_866fdf07312224c.png</url><title>Completed</title><link>/tag/completed/</link></image><item><title>MLSysOps</title><link>/projects/mlsysops/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/mlsysops/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NUBIS contribution:&lt;/strong&gt; As WP3 leader, NUBIS orchestrated the development of efficient mechanisms for optimizing application execution, resource utilization and energy consumption across the whole continuum.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>NEPHELE: DROP</title><link>/projects/nephele-drop/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/nephele-drop/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NUBIS contribution:&lt;/strong&gt; Through the DROP proposal, NUBIS develops a distributed resource offloading mechanism leveraging the vAccel framework for ESP32-based IoT devices. DROP enables real-time processing capabilities for resource-constrained devices while reducing latency and improving system efficiency, fostering innovation in logistics, smart home, and industrial automation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>DESIRE6G</title><link>/projects/desire6g/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/desire6g/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NUBIS contribution:&lt;/strong&gt; As WP3 leader, NUBIS designed and developed a lightweight, ultra-performant SMO for Desire6G, able to scale out compute-intensive parts of service decomposition as standalone, scalable serverless functions. Additionally, NUBIS enabled interoperable hardware acceleration mechanisms for full data-plane programmability.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>SERRANO</title><link>/projects/serrano/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/serrano/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NUBIS contribution:&lt;/strong&gt; Involved in the systems software development, to enable transparent and interoperable execution of various types of workloads as standalone enclaves (containers, microVMs, VMs and unikernels), as well as in the security hardening of devices and application attestation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>5G-COMPLETE</title><link>/projects/5g-complete/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/5g-complete/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NUBIS contribution:&lt;/strong&gt; Involved in the MEC systems software, as well as the application deployment. Introduced Secure boot, application attestation and secure, cloud-native deployments for MEC-related applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>