<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>FOSSCOMM | Nubificus</title>
    <link>/tag/fosscomm/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/fosscomm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>FOSSCOMM</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 08:10:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/logo_hu_f553cb9eef83bc41.png</url>
      <title>FOSSCOMM</title>
      <link>/tag/fosscomm/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fosscomm 2024</title>
      <link>/blog/fosscomm-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 08:10:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/fosscomm-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re into open-source and tech meetups, FOSSCOMM is the event to be at. This year, it was held in Thessaloniki, organized by the open-source community of the University of Macedonia (UoM), and they absolutely crushed it with the setup and vibe!&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-main-entrance----uom-building&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/images/fosscomm2.jpg#center&#34; alt=&#34;Main Entrance -- UoM building&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Main Entrance &amp;ndash; UoM building
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atmosphere was awesome—super inclusive and welcoming, with folks from all over Greece and beyond coming together to celebrate open-source software. Whether you were a newcomer or a seasoned developer, everyone felt part of the community, sharing knowledge, projects, and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were lucky to give two talks at this year’s FOSSCOMM! The first one was about k8s, CRDs, and how we’re using them to tailor k8s clusters to fit our projects&amp;rsquo; needs. If you’re curious, here’s the &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.nephos.gr/fosscomm/2024/FOSSCOMM-2024-NUBIS-k8s-crd.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;slide deck&lt;/a&gt; for that session. We also demoed some of our work—check out the video &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/1KJ5ikE4ndNd1TPvWpjCBKVfhscbKMBGk/preview&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, we built a step-by-step tutorial for this at &lt;a href=&#34;https://killercoda.com/nubis/scenario/CRD_Etherpad&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Killercoda&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-panos-mavrikos-talking-about-k8s-operators--crds&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/images/fosscomm1.jpg#center&#34; alt=&#34;Panos Mavrikos talking about k8s operators &amp; CRDs&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Panos Mavrikos talking about k8s operators &amp;amp; CRDs
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second talk tackled sandboxing workloads in cloud-edge environments, exploring flexibility and performance, the role of hardware accelerators, and how these all impact cloud-edge use cases. It was an exciting session, sparking lots of ideas around security and efficiency. Here’s the &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.nephos.gr/fosscomm/2024/FOSSCOMM-2024-NUBIS-hwaccel.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;slide deck&lt;/a&gt; and three demo videos for this talk: &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.nephos.gr/fosscomm/2024/Bert-torch-vaccel-correct.mp4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Demo 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.nephos.gr/fosscomm/2024/SOL-torch-vaccel.mp4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Demo 2&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.nephos.gr/fosscomm/2024/vaccel-tvm.mov&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Demo 3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-anastassios-nanos-talking-about-hardware-acceleration-in-sandboxed-environments&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/images/fosscomm4.jpg#center&#34; alt=&#34;Anastassios Nanos talking about hardware acceleration in sandboxed environments&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Anastassios Nanos talking about hardware acceleration in sandboxed environments
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program was absolutely packed this year, with tons of insightful sessions for anyone into open-source, cloud, DevOps, education, IoT, and more! Here are just a couple of standout talks from the packed weekend that really captured the spirit of innovation and open knowledge sharing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lessons from the Unix History&amp;rdquo; by Professor Diomidis Spinellis from AUEB: A must-see for any history and tech lovers, this talk walked us through the evolution of Unix, exploring its massive influence on modern operating systems and open-source culture. If you’ve ever wondered how Unix’s legacy continues to impact today’s software, this was the place to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Running a Company on Free Software: The First 20 Years&amp;rdquo; by Apollon Oikonomopoulos, CIO of Skroutz: Apollon shared an inspiring journey of building and managing the core infrastructure of a successful business using free software for over two decades. This talk was especially interesting for anyone wondering about the practicalities of relying on open-source tools in a business setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How to Build a Sustainable Open Source Company&amp;rdquo; by Frank Karlitschek, CEO of NextCloud: Frank brought tons of insight into what it takes to not just create open-source software but to build a thriving, sustainable business around it. This session had great takeaways on balancing open-source ideals with business realities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Quo Vadis, Free Software? Quo Vadis, Society?&amp;rdquo; by Luis Falcon, Founder of GNU Solidario: A thought-provoking talk on the societal role of free software, and the vision of a world where open-source tech powers humanitarian causes. This session looked at how free software can impact issues like healthcare and education and was a great reminder of the deeper purpose driving open-source communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;EdgeAI: A HW-SW Codesign Approach&amp;rdquo; by George Keramidas from Aristotle University of Thessaloniki: This one was a treat for those interested in the cutting-edge (literally!) of AI at the hardware level. George explored the integration of hardware and software for AI at the edge, showing how open-source innovation is shaping this critical area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/images/images/fosscomm3.jpg#floatleft&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it wasn’t just about the talks. FOSSCOMM this year was a hub of energy, ideas, and connections! The booth setups were fantastic, ranging from beginner-friendly intros to cutting-edge tech demos. And the people—wow. We met a huge range of enthusiasts, from students trying open-source for the first time to veterans in the field sharing their latest work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big shoutout to the entire organizing team for a smooth, engaging event. Everything ran like clockwork, and you could really tell how much care went into making it a positive, collaborative space. If you’re thinking of attending next year, don’t hesitate—FOSSCOMM always delivers, and we can’t wait to see what’s in store for next time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to FOSSCOMM 2025!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
